I think something here about violence and how we
interviolence resonates with people and the image
and the way you made it.
So I mean, do you have things to offer with this one?
So interesting that that's the one you chose.
I wasn't expecting that.
But I love that.
I mean, to me, this image, I really
wanted to do that quote because it speaks to me
as someone who has, like most of us, all of us,
has deep experience with being on many sides of violence.
And I both had, like many of us who've
been in the movement for a long time.
I mean, there's such destructive, even by many, many people
who are well known as abolitionists, thinkers, and teachers,
and practitioners, how do we actually
practice this in our lives?
Are we ostracizing people in our communities?
Are we allowing for the possibility of transformation
and redemption and sanctuary?
Or are we just saying, especially with people,
like trans people of color and other folks who just
have so little support?
Are we saying, well, go die?
This is the only community where you get to live.
And we no longer welcome you and goodbye.
And I just see that so much and have experienced versions
of that myself.
And I think as an artist, when you talk about what's scary,
I mean, we have to talk about it.
I used to think it was just me, but as I continued for decades
to make art in the movement, privately,
the number of artists and thinkers and just cultural workers
who reach out to me privately and say, OK,
I've had this situation for years with someone
accusing me of terrible things that I did not do.
And honestly, even if you did them,
isn't the point of abolition that you get a chance
that you are not disposable.
So I think artists are especially
a risk for community repribution
because our work is so public.
And I have certainly experienced that.
And the people who are in my life,
who are my informant, who are my family,
who are all of this work has a very deep, informal advisory
committee who are like my family, who say, oh my god,
nope, that analysis is off or her chin looks wrong or whatever.
And yeah, so just to me, this text speaks
to the fact that we all have many different experiences
in relation to violence.
And if we're going to be honest, we need to talk about that.
I also love this piece.
And I teach with this one.
I think I have a lot of students who come.
And I think it's really easy to do this myself.
Who come to you thinking about violence
with that good bad binary with the victim offender binary?
And it's just it's not a sustainable way
to think for the kinds of futures we talk about building.
And I would love for you to explain why a volcano?
And is that water in front of the volcano?
And if so, why that juxtaposition?
Yeah, tell us a little bit more about the process and the rationale.
And if you would read the Sir Ed quote,
which is just foundational to my life,
like this piece is so important.
It's just like that quote is like a guiding beacon in my daily life.
So this piece really resonates with me.
And I'd love to hear you just describe it.
I want to come to your class and listen to teach about this piece.
So the quote says, no one enters violence
for the first time by committing it.
And there's an image of a active volcano erupting
in front of a black story sky.
And the lava is flowing down into those.
And there's something about the fact
that a volcano is a perfect example of how violence can be
part of world building, earth building,
and part of our foundations and can build new land that
can transform and become fertile.
And also how we need the ocean.
We need oceans that can cool and that are very difficult,
hot molten lava can flow into.
So this one's intense.
Yeah.
Thank you.
It sounds intense because it is like a someone
who's been violent and struggles with those kinds of issues.
When I look at this, I'm like, this is how it feels.
And then I keep looking and to have the ocean,
that possibility of whether we think about it as accountability
or cooling off space somewhere to just be safe and like,
yeah, try to.
I love the idea of the molten hardening
and it becoming like this rejuvenating kind of healing process.
Like that was a really beautiful description.
Thank you so much.
When I think the first time I saw it,
and then when I saw it, I mean, my students' reactions in class,
they often choose this one.
They like this one a lot.
And I think it's because I don't know.
I mean, but what they tell me on the basis of what they tell me
on the basis of how I see people using it,
it gives us a space to be seen in who we are,
which is people who commit harm and people
who have harm committed against us.
And so there is a space where we really can be.
And people want that.
I mean, in all this world of binaries,
they want the ways to break through.
And so it does an amazing kind of work for us all.
I think, did you want to add to that, Micah?
Well, I'm still thinking about what, you know,
sort of the behind the scenes, behind the curtain,
kind of ways that artists experience punishment
and the movement for our just practicing
and public, you know, being human
for the ways that art is complex and not literal all the time.
And especially really marginalized artists like, you know,
trans women and trans women artists and other folks,
like, you know, once turf skin onto them.
And it just, it just how much people I know
are suffering and pain for this and not defended
by our movements because of the cancel culture
in our movements.
And I'm really looking forward to a time
in our movements when that changes.
I don't know they'll be in my lifetime,
but, you know, the people don't talk about enough
in my opinion, the cost that movement arts
go through privately for our work.